Inventory of the Daniel A. Nelson Bicentennial collection, 1923-1989 (bulk 1975-1977)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Daniel A. Nelson Bicentennial collection
1923-1989 (bulk 1975-1977)
Nelson, Daniel A.
06182
27.20 cubic ft. (26 boxes)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
The Daniel A. Nelson Bicentennial collection contains subject files, publications, articles, events, memorabilia and merchandise for America's bicentennial celebration in 1976. In addition, there is miscellaneous material from the mid 1970s.
Arrangement of the Collection
This collection has been minimally processed and arranged in two series.
Biography of Daniel A. Nelson
Daniel A. Nelson was a junior high school teacher and director of the Laramie Plains Museum in Laramie, Wyoming. He incorporated the celebration of the Bicentennial into teaching lessons, was involved with local planning of celebrations, and collected Bicentennial Memorabilia.
Scope and Content
This collection contains Daniel A. Nelson's Bicentennial memorabilia and souvenirs collected primarily in the Laramie, Wyoming region. The material in this collection is representative of how the region and America celebrated the American Revolution Bicentennial in 1976. Found in the collection are Bicentennial themed calendars, book covers, posters, syrup bottles, soda cans, grocery bags, commemorative plates, tshirts and a flag. Also Included in this collection are desk calendars, placemats, mobiles, pencils, bumper stickers, sugar packets, potholders, reproductions of the U.S. Constitution, stickers, Town meeting posters, newspaper clippings, correspondence, bicentennial merchandise catalogs, miscellaneous bicentennial era newspapers and periodicals as well as Laramie Bicentennial materials. An assortment of subject files in this collection relate to Dan Nelson's Bicentennial era high school curriculum and include headings such as "Bicentennial ideas from students", "Buffalo project", "Bikecentennial", "Fire hydrant projects", "Contests", "My America contest", "Junior committee of correspondence", "Bicentennial youth debates" and National Educational Association Bicentennial plans". These subject files also include various educational material catalogs and educational newsletters such as "Bicentennial Times". This collection also contains bicentennial era brochures, pamphlets, publications, tourism brochures, and popular culture magazines and catalogs from the bicentennial era.
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
There are no known other archival collections created by at the date of processing.
This collection was donated by Daniel A. Nelson in multiple accretions from 1986-1999.
Access Terms
American Revolution Bicentennial Administration; American Revolution Bicentennial Commission of Wyoming; American Revolution Bicentennial, 1976 -- Wyoming -- Laramie;;; Laramie (Wyo.); Wyoming -- History -- 1946-
Wyoming; Politics and Politicians; Military; City and Town Life
Container List
- Series I. Bicentennial Related Material
  This series includes materials created (in one way or another) for the Bicentennial celebration. In addition to calendars, published articles, and memorabilia, there is information on events, tourist attractions, merchandise, and teaching lessons. The subject files include publications, correspondence, events, and event planning documents created by the American Revolution Bicentennial Administration and Commission.
  - Calendars, 1976 (Box 1, 26)
  - Magazine and Newspaper Articles, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Memorabilia, circa 1976 (Box 2-4, 26)
  - Merchandise and Products Relating to the Bicentennial, circa 1976 (Box 1)
  - Subject Files, circa 1976 (Box 5-7)
  - Tourism Brochures Related to Bicentennial, 1976 (Box 8)
  - University of Wyoming Events and Material, 1976 (Box 8)
- Series II. 1976-Era Miscellaneous Material
  Contains calenders, teaching materials, publications, mail-order catalogs, tourism brochures, University of Wyoming materials, and information on Wyoming.
  - Calendars, circa 1976 (Box 8, 26)
  - Laramie High School and Teaching Material, 1923-1977 (Box 9)
  - Magazines and Newspapers, 1971-1989 (Box 9-13)
  - Mail received by Nelson, circa 1976 (Box 14)
  - Merchandise (Mail order catalogs), 1955-1977 (Box 15-20)
  - Tourism Brochures, circa 1976 (Box 21-23)
  - University of Wyoming Material, 1934-1977 (Box 24)
  - Wyoming, 1966-1976 (Box 25)